<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The agreement and resolution of severall associated ministers in the County of Corke for the ordaining of ministers</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75967</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A768A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R70</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077454</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077454</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151511</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75967)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151511)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2261:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The agreement and resolution of severall associated ministers in the County of Corke for the ordaining of ministers</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Willam Smith for Richard Plummer ... ,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Corke :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1657]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Henry E. Huntington Library, San Marino, California.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ordination.</term>
               <term>Clergy --  Ireland.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151511:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE AGREEMENT AND RESOLVTION OF SEVERALL ASSOCIATED MINISTERS <hi>IN THE COUNTY OF CORKE</hi> FOR THE ORDAINING OF MINISTERS.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MAT: 9.37, 38.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Then ſaith he unto his Diſciples, The harveſt truely is plenteous, but the Labourers are few. Pray the Lord of the harveſt, that he will ſend forth Labourers into his harvest.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 TIM: 2.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And the things that thou haſt heard of me, among many witneſſes, the ſame commit thou to faithfull men, who ſhall be able to teach others alſo.</p>
            </q>
            <p>CORKE.</p>
            <p>¶ Printed by WILLIAM SMITH for <hi>Richard Plummer,</hi> and are to be ſold at his houſe in Corke.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:151511:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151511:2"/>
            <head>THE WORKE OF THE MINISTRY <hi>PERPETUALLY NECESSARY TO THE</hi> CHVRCH-MILITANT.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">§. 1.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He worke of the Miniſtry is, as well of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall neceſſity, as of ſpirituall advantage to the Church-Militant; To reſtraine, 2 <hi>Cron:</hi> 24.2. To call, 2. <hi>Theſ:</hi> 2.14. To convert, <hi>Act:</hi> 26.16, 17, 18. To expound the Divine will, <hi>Act:</hi> 8.31. To make known the manifold wiſdom of GOD, <hi>Eph:</hi> 3.7, ad <hi>verſe</hi> 10, and heart ſecrets of men, <hi>Heb:</hi> 4.12. To miniſter the Spirit, 2. <hi>Cor:</hi> 3.8. <hi>Gal:</hi> 3.2, 5; which is not promiſed to teach any thing but what CHRIST hath ſpoken before, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 14.26; and <hi>Iohn</hi> makes it to be the infallible examen, or tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of the <hi>Spirits,</hi> whether they be of GOD, or not, That they conſent that CHRIST is come in the fleſh, 1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3, and heare, that is, obey his word by his appointed Miniſtry, which he profeſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly determines to be of GOD, <hi>verſe</hi> 6. To worke Faith, <hi>Rom:</hi> 10, 14. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 3.5. <hi>Ioh:</hi> 17.20. To ſanctify, <hi>Ioh:</hi> 17.17. To eſtabliſh, <hi>Eph:</hi> 4.14. To
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151511:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſeale, <hi>Eph:</hi> 1.13. To come with; and convey much aſſurance, with evidence of Divine Election, 1 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 1.4, 5, &amp; joy in the Holy GHOST, <hi>v:</hi> 6. To convince <hi>Gain-ſayers,</hi> and ſtop the Mouths of <hi>Deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Tit:</hi> 1.9, 11, whereunto the Church Militant is in all Ages obnoxious, 2 <hi>Pet:</hi> 2.1. 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 4.2. Elect Ones ſhall (if is were poſſible) be deceived (<hi>Math:</hi> 24.24) by the uncertaine ſound of <hi>Schiſmes</hi> brazen Trumpets, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 14.8: <hi>Zions</hi> Silver ones are needfull to call her Aſſemblies, <hi>Numb,</hi> 10.7, and alarum her <hi>Sons</hi> to battel, <hi>v,</hi> 9. Every Hereticke, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, will in theſe laſt, and perilous times be pointing at CHRIST, with a <hi>Loe</hi> here, <hi>Loe</hi> there is CHRIST, is if he were there in ſober ſadneſs, <hi>Math:</hi> 24.23, 24: There is a neceſſity of the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of theſe <hi>Philips</hi> to lead doubting <hi>Nathaniels</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to JESVS, <hi>Ioh:</hi> 1.46: ignorant <hi>Eunuchs</hi> to a right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the word, <hi>Act:</hi> 8.30. to <hi>v.</hi> 35, &amp; to a due participation of the Sacraments, <hi>v:</hi> 36, 37, 38. The world lyes in wickedneſs, 1 <hi>Ioh:</hi> 5.19, in thicke, groſs, <hi>Egyptian</hi> darkneſs, <hi>Ioh:</hi> 1.5.3.19: theſe <hi>Lights</hi> muſt flame on the hill, <hi>Math:</hi> 5.14: in the Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick <hi>v.</hi> 15: to diſpell, and breake it, <hi>v:</hi> 16. Falſe Apoſtles, will fill their hands, or <hi>conſecrate</hi> them ſelves, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 13.33: theſe <hi>Epheſine</hi> Angels muſt try them, <hi>Rev:</hi> 2, 2. <hi>Jezabel</hi> will make hereſelfe a Propheteſs to teach, and to ſeduce: theſe Thyatirian Angels muſt prohibit her, <hi>Rev:</hi> 2.20. Diotrephes's, men loving preheminence, will exerciſe arbitrary power in the Churches; Others ſhall not be <hi>Miniſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers;</hi> They will be <hi>Maſters:</hi> there muſt be a ſucceſſion of authorized <hi>Iohns</hi> to remember their deeds, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151511:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſilence their pratings. 3 <hi>Ioh: v:</hi> 9, 10. Conſuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s will multiply in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> till there be neither meaſure, nor end of them, unleſs ſome <hi>Pauls</hi> be in being &amp; carefull to <hi>ſet things in order</hi> when they come, 1. <hi>Cor:</hi> 11.34. Many Children will want their food; and allowance, if at any time there be none in Office, <hi>Stewards</hi> of the Myſteries, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold wiſdome of GOD, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 4.1. 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 4.10. CHRISTS co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming can not be as it was in the dayes of <hi>Noah, Math:</hi> 24.37, unleſs ſome <hi>Preacher</hi> of righteouſneſs be then living, 2 <hi>Pet:</hi> 2.5, to <hi>warne</hi> the ſinfull world of their wickedneſs, and danger. The pureſt <hi>graine</hi> hath its <hi>chaffe,</hi> 1. <hi>Ioh:</hi> 1.8, 10. <hi>Pro:</hi> 20.9: the beſt need this <hi>Fanne</hi> to cleanſe them, <hi>Math:</hi> 3.12. Sheep are apt to <hi>wander, Pſal:</hi> 119.176. <hi>Eſa:</hi> 53.6: the beſt need a <hi>Nathan</hi> to <hi>reduce</hi> them, 2 <hi>Sam:</hi> 12.7. All fleſh is liable to <hi>Fly-blows, Eccl:</hi> 7.20: the beſt neede this <hi>ſalt</hi> to preſerve them, <hi>Math:</hi> 5.13. Where grace is not, the worke of the Miniſtry is neceſſary to <hi>beget</hi> it, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 4.15. <hi>Jam:</hi> 1.18: where grace is, the worke of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry is neceſſary to <hi>continue</hi> it, 1 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 5.19, 20. to <hi>increaſe</hi> it, <hi>Act:</hi> 20 28. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. As long as there is one <hi>Sinner</hi> to be <hi>converted,</hi> one <hi>Saint</hi> to be <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected,</hi> one <hi>member</hi> in the body of CHRIST to be <hi>edified,</hi> one Chriſtian <hi>militant</hi> to be made <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant,</hi> the worke of the Miniſtry is neceſſary, <hi>Math:</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Eph:</hi> 4.11, 12. <hi>Act:</hi> 20.32.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:151511:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Office-power perpetually neceſſary to the work of the Miniſtry.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">§. 2.</note>AS much as the Ability, or <hi>Gift</hi> is in order to the <hi>Office,</hi> or Adminiſtration: So much is the <hi>Office</hi> in order to the <hi>Worke,</hi> or Operation, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 12.4.5.6. 1 The worke of labouring in the word, and Doctrine, is the diſtinctive character of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours. 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 5.17. <hi>Eph:</hi> 4.12. 2 Thoſe only are gifted for the worke of the Miniſtry, <hi>for</hi> whom CHRIST <hi>received, to</hi> whom CHRIST <hi>gave</hi> Gifts; &amp; theſe in the Holy GHOSTS Regiſter, are only gifted Church-Officers, <hi>Eph:</hi> 4.11, 12, 13. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 68.18. 3 <hi>Office-power</hi> is ſo eſſentiall, that if the Office-worke may be done by others then inſtituted Officers, 1 Poſitive acts of Religion neede not an <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative</hi> warrant. 2 The inſtitution of Officers had been <hi>ſuperfluous.</hi> 3 GODS Judgments againſt <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truders,</hi> had been unjuſt; <hi>(abſie)</hi> Nor was that, which the Scripture makes to be the extreame of <hi>Jeroboams</hi> Apoſtacy, any ſo great matter, 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 12.31. cap: 13.33. Nor that ſad threatning of the Church of <hi>Jſrael</hi> by the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> any thing at all, <hi>Hoſ:</hi> 4.9. Read alſo and conſider <hi>Jer:</hi> 23.21. 1 <hi>Sam:</hi> 13.13. 2 <hi>Sam:</hi> 6.7.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The diſtinction of the Miniſteriall-Office.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">§. 3.</note>TO run without <hi>Office-power,</hi> argues <hi>preſumption;</hi> to ſtand ſtill with it, <hi>lazineſs:</hi> The former, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Miniſtry is a diſtinct <hi>Office:</hi> The latter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it impowers for diſtinct <hi>Workes,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 3.1. 1 The Perſons <hi>impower'd</hi> diſtinct; ſome, <hi>Eph:</hi> 4.11: not all, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 11.29; and in relation to their Office,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151511:4"/>diſtinguiſhed from other Saints. <hi>Heb:</hi> 13.24. 2 The <hi>Office,</hi> &amp; Office-titles diſtinct; 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 3.1. <hi>Ier:</hi> 3.15. <hi>Math:</hi> 9.36, 37, 38. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 3.9.4.1.2.15. 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 3.6.5.20. <hi>Act:</hi> 20.28. <hi>Rev:</hi> 1.16, 20. 3 diſtinct promiſes are made to Church-Officers, <hi>Mat:</hi> 10.19.16.19.18.18.28.20. 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 4.16. 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 5.4. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3. 4 diſtinct <hi>gifts,</hi> and qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations required in them, 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 3.2. <hi>Tit:</hi> 1.7, 8, 9. 5 diſtinct <hi>duties</hi> impoſed on <hi>them</hi> concerning others, 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 5.2, 3. 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 4.13, 14, 15. 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 4.2. <hi>Heb:</hi> 13.17: the neglect whereof procures <hi>Woe</hi> peculiarly to them, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 9.16; is <hi>reproved</hi> peculiarly in them, and for the obſervance, they peculiarly <hi>approved, Rev:</hi> 2. cap: 3. 6 diſtinct <hi>Duties</hi> impoſed on <hi>others</hi> concerning them, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 16.10, 11, 15, 16, 17, 18. 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 8.23, 24. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 9. <hi>Gal:</hi> 6.6. 1 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 5.12, 13. 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 5.17. <hi>Heb:</hi> 13.7. <hi>Phil:</hi> 2.29: the obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance wherof in the loweſt meaſure is kindly accepted by CHRIST, <hi>Math:</hi> 10.40. <hi>Ioh:</hi> 13.20: the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect <hi>condemned</hi> as the worſt of Sins, 2 <hi>Cron:</hi> 36.15, 16. <hi>Lu:</hi> 10.16. <hi>Hoſ:</hi> 4.4: Reſiſters of <hi>them</hi> are ſaid to <hi>reſiſt</hi> the Holy GHOST: <hi>Act:</hi> 7.51, 52: diſpiſers of them are ſaid to be <hi>deſpiſers</hi> of GOD, 1 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 4.8: to judge themſelves <hi>unworthy</hi> of eternall life. <hi>Act:</hi> 13.46: to <hi>reject</hi> the counſell of GOD againſt themſelves, <hi>Lu:</hi> 7.30: <hi>punniſhed</hi> with the worſt of judgments, 2 <hi>Cron:</hi> 36.16, 17. 1 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 2.16. 2 <hi>Kings.</hi> 2.24. <hi>Amos.</hi> 2.12, to <hi>v.</hi> 16. The Apoſtle <hi>Jude, v.</hi> 11. taxeth the <hi>primitive Hereticks</hi> with three horrid crimes againſt Chriſtianity, 1 <hi>Cruelty</hi> againſt their Brethren, as <hi>Cain.</hi> 2 <hi>Vaſſalling Religion</hi> under covetouſneſs, as <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam.</hi> 3 <hi>Oppoſition</hi> to the miniſterial Function, as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151511:5"/>
                  <hi>Core:</hi> and adjoines <hi>periſhing</hi> as the neceſſary <hi>product</hi> of that contradiction. To this Sin, <hi>temporall</hi> punniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are often conſequent, 2 <hi>Cron:</hi> 36.17. <hi>Amos.</hi> 2.12, to <hi>v.</hi> 16. 2 <hi>Kings.</hi> 2.24; <hi>Spirituall</hi> alwaies. That dreadfull <hi>judgment</hi> threatned <hi>Iſai:</hi> 6.9, 10, and ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten repeated in the new Teſtament,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat:</hi> 13. <hi>Mar:</hi> 4.12. <hi>Lu:</hi> 8.10. <hi>Ioh:</hi> 12.40. <hi>Act:</hi> 28.26. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.8.</note> (where Gods diſpenſations, both in mercies, and judgements, are eſpecially <hi>ſpirituall</hi>) in each of the <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> in the <hi>Acts,</hi> and in the Epiſtles, is the ſpeciall fruit of this impiety. When thoſe who are <hi>antiminiſteriall,</hi> reele ſo faſt to <hi>Atheiſine,</hi> and a <hi>ſottiſh inſenſibility,</hi> let none imagine that GOD leaves them unpuniſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The diſtinct miniſteriall-werke, and Office proved by Reaſon.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">§. 4.</note>THough grace doth <hi>unbeaſt</hi> us: yet it doth not <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> us. The will of GOD therefore diſcovered by <hi>right reaſon,</hi> binds our obſervance: and <hi>right reaſon</hi> gives in its ſuffrage to the diſtinct worke, and Office of the Miniſtry, as 1 From the <hi>nature</hi> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Ordinances, which are 1 High, and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult; ſuch as require the <hi>whole</hi> time, 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 4.15: yea more than the <hi>whole</hi> man, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 2.16. 2 <hi>Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,</hi> and <hi>excellent:</hi> myſterious, becauſe <hi>religious</hi> (of inward <hi>grace</hi> as well as outward <hi>rites</hi>) excellent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe myſterious; And the difficulty, <hi>Act:</hi> 6.2, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, <hi>Heb:</hi> 5.4, and myſteriouſneſs, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 4.1. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16, as of every Employment: ſo eſpecially of that which is ſacred, diſtinguiſheth Perſons to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it. 2 From the <hi>manner</hi> of religious duties; A worke done in religion is not done, if the <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> of doing confutes the <hi>matter</hi> of the thing done,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151511:5"/>1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 11.17, 20. <hi>Hoſ:</hi> 7.14: But ſuch as are regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, <hi>Who</hi> performes religious cuties, are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardleſs <hi>whether,</hi> alwaies regardleſs <hi>how,</hi> they are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. 1 <hi>Kings.</hi> 12.31, 32. 3 From the <hi>end</hi> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the deligne whereof is GODS glory; <hi>i.e.</hi> the manifeſtation of divine excellency. 1 GODS <hi>Being</hi> is manifeſted, when as in the darker glaſs of the world: ſo in the <hi>clearer</hi> glaſs of the Church (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting more lively GODS Image, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 3.18) by this <hi>dependance.</hi> of one on another, we are led to him the <hi>originall</hi> of all. 2 GODS <hi>Power</hi> is manifeſted, when by ſuch <hi>neake</hi> diſtinct Inſtruments of divine appointment, 1 <hi>Nations</hi> propoſſeſſed with enmity, and prejudice, are <hi>ſubdued</hi> to owne the way of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 1.27, 28. 2 The heart (which is GODS privy-chamber) is <hi>reached: Paul</hi> a priſoner at the <hi>barre,</hi> makes <hi>Felix,</hi> a Judge on the <hi>bench</hi> to tremble, <hi>Act:</hi> 24.25. <hi>Agrippa</hi> becemes <hi>almoſt</hi> a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> at one of the ſame <hi>priſoner-preachers</hi> Sermons, <hi>Act:</hi> 26.28. 3. <hi>Supernaturall</hi> treatures are conveyed by <hi>earthen</hi> veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells; the power therfore is of GOD, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 4.7: upon which account the Apoſtle puts Faith, wrought by Goſpell-preaching in the firſt ranke of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable things of the great day, 2 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 1.10. 3 GODS univerſall <hi>Soveraignty</hi> is manifeſted by our united ſervices, (as ſociable creatures), which are required of us, <hi>Heb:</hi> 10.25: and can not be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by us, without diſtinct Ordinances, nor thoſe <hi>orderly</hi> adminiſtred, without diſtinct Officers; And as GOD is the GOD of order in the whole Univerſe: ſo eſpecially in the Churches of the Saints. 4 GODS goodneſs is manifeſted by imploying 1 ſuch diſtinct
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151511:6"/>Iuſtruments, as are ſymbolicall, and therfore moſt probable to be effectuall, <hi>Ex:</hi> 20.19. 2 Such as may in their lives <hi>exemplify,</hi> what in their doctrines they teach, <hi>Phil:</hi> 3.17 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 4.12. 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 5.3. 3 ſuch as have their <hi>adventurers</hi> in the ſame veſſell, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 1.6, 8: So that they can not deceive others, but they muſt deceive themſelves, <hi>Math</hi> 15.14. 5 GODS <hi>wiſdome</hi> is manifeſted, in the inſtitution of this diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inct double witneſs <hi>Ioh:</hi> 15.26, 27; double meanes; 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 3.9; inward, and outward. GOD is a <hi>Spirit,</hi> his conveyances of himſelfe muſt be <hi>ſpirituall:</hi> we are <hi>Bodies,</hi> our preſent receptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s muſt be corporeall; ſo the infinite <hi>wiſdome</hi> of our GOD, that ſuits his <hi>institutes</hi> to both; to the former by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of his grace; to the latter by the Miniſtry of Man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That it is, <hi>GOD,</hi> who calls to the Office<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke, and power miniſteriall.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">§. 5.</note>BUt all <hi>meanes</hi> ought to be proportioned to their proper <hi>ends.</hi> The Streame can not riſe higher then the ſpring-head; As therfore the <hi>ends</hi> ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the <hi>inſtitution</hi> of the Miniſtry is <hi>ſupernaturalls</hi> Not to ſpeake of the <hi>Poieſt-hood,</hi> before, and under <hi>Moſaicall Paedagogie;</hi> GOD promiſeth, <hi>Eſa:</hi> 66.21, to ſingle, or <hi>take</hi> out from the reſt of beleevers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpell; ſome for <hi>Priestes,</hi>) and <hi>Levites, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es</hi> New-Teſtament Officers, ſet forth in old Teſtament characters: And according to this promiſe, GOD <hi>ſets</hi> ſuch in the Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28, 29, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5, 18.19. Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>gives</hi> them to the Church, <hi>Ephe</hi> 4.11 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.11 12 The Holy GHOST <hi>ſeperates</hi> them for the Church, <hi>Act:</hi> 13.2.20.28.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:151511:6"/>
               <head>Ordinary Ministers.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">§. 6.</note>THis truth reacheth, not only Apoſtles, Prop hets and Evangeliſts <hi>(extraordinary):</hi> but Paſt ours and Teachers alſo <hi>(ordinary)</hi> Church-officers: Thus <hi>Apollo,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 3.5. Epaphras, <hi>Col:</hi> 1.7. Archippus, <hi>Col:</hi> 4.17. Silvanus, 1 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 1.10, with cap: 2.4. Tychicus, <hi>Col:</hi> 4.7. <hi>Eph:</hi> 6.21, ordinary Miniſters, received their Miniſtry from the LORD.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And mediately by Miniſters.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">§. 7.</note>ANd as it is perpetually neceſſary, that thoſe, who miniſter in the things of GOD, ſhould be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſeperated by GOD: ſo is it perpetually neceſſary, that by ſome <hi>externall act,</hi> it might appeare, who are thus ſeparated. This <hi>Expreſs</hi> under the Goſpell, Chriſt at firſt determined, either by perſonall, or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous ſignation. Perſonall, during his humiliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the 12 Apoſtles, <hi>Math:</hi> 10: Miraculous, after his aſcenſion, as <hi>Matthias</hi> by <hi>Lot Act:</hi> 1.26. <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> by <hi>viſion, Act:</hi> 13.2. <hi>Timothy</hi> by propheſy, 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 4.14. But though <hi>Miracles</hi> ceaſe, yet the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell-miniſtration, and Miniſtry muſt continue (2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 3.11,) in regard that the Churches <hi>neede</hi> of it, (as Sect: 1.), &amp; GODs <hi>care</hi> to ſupply it, is the ſame to the end, <hi>Math:</hi> 16.18. &amp; 24.14. <hi>Eſa:</hi> 30.20. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth CHRIST <hi>ſend</hi> Goſpell-Miniſters, as the FATHER ſent him, <hi>Ioh:</hi> 20.21: &amp; <hi>authorizeth</hi> them (acting under him, and in his ſtead, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.20.) to authorize others, 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.2. And as their worke &amp; office ſhall continue to the end of the world: ſo he promiſeth his preſence with them alwaies, even to the end of the world, <hi>Mith:</hi> 28.18, 19, 20.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:151511:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>By the way of Ordination.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">§. 8.</note>THe Miniſters of the Goſpell thus ſeparated and authorized to ſeparate and authorize others; are herein directed to <hi>Goſpel Ordination;</hi> as GODS <hi>inſtitution</hi> for this end and purpoſe. Thus <hi>Paul;</hi> though <hi>immediately</hi> choſen by GOD, even to an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolate, muſt be ordained, <hi>Act:</hi> 13.1.2: and the <hi>Seven,</hi> though <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mediately</hi> choſen by the multitude of diſciples, but even a <hi>Deaconſhip,</hi> muſt be ordained, <hi>Act:</hi> 6.3, 6. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> goe from place to place, to ordaine <hi>Preſbyters</hi> in every City. <hi>Act:</hi> 14.23. <hi>Titus</hi> is left at <hi>Crete</hi> to ordaine <hi>Presbyters, Tit:</hi> 1.5: all which had been nedleſs, if <hi>qualifications,</hi> or popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>election</hi> (without ordination) had been authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative <hi>miſſion. Timothy</hi> received his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion by the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery, 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 4.14: and though in the <hi>negative,</hi> he be forbad to lay hands ſudenly on any man: yet thereby in the <hi>affirmative,</hi> he is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to lay on hands, <hi>i. e.</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine Miniſters, 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 5.22.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Goſpell-Miniſters (in the County of Corke) excited to ordaine Ministers.</head>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>
                     <hi>1</hi> By Sence of Duty.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">§. 9.</note>VVE doe not, we dare not <hi>apologize</hi> for all, or any the infirmities, errors, offences, ſcandalls &amp;c, of any in the Miniſtry. It is (the LORD knows) a cauſe of ſadneſs, and heart-ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to us, as often as we thinke of them; and the rather, conſidering how prodigiouſly provoking,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151511:7"/>and of what dangerous, deſtructive conſequence, the exceſſes and obliquities of the <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>Levi</hi> are, which the LORD hath been wont to proſecute with flaming expreſſions of an hot diſpleaſure, <hi>Mal:</hi> 2.8, 9: Yet ſince the unbeleife &amp; miſcarriages of men can not make the faith of GOD of none effect in any thing that he hath promiſed to his Church, <hi>Rom:</hi> 3.3. 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.13: and ſince, even in the deepeſt defection of the <hi>Aaronicall Prieſt-hood,</hi> which was to give place in time to the <hi>Evangelicall,</hi> GOD tooke care, ere he <hi>threw out</hi> one, to provide for the <hi>ſubstitution</hi> of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as if he would thereby acquaint us, that it is ſome part of the myſtery of his waies, to be angry with men in Office, and <hi>well pleaſed</hi> with the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Office it ſelfe at one and the ſame time as we may ſee in that famous portion of Scripture, 1 <hi>Sam:</hi> 2.27 <hi>ad fin:</hi> Yea, eſpecially, ſince we are incompaſſed with ſuch a cloud of <hi>Scripture-teſtimonies</hi> already expreſſed, That GOD will not leave his Church at any time, after the manifeſtation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of his <hi>Son,</hi> deſtitute of Paſtours, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his own heart, which ſhall to the end of the world teach, and make Diſciples out of all Nations; unto whom our LORD JESVS hath annexed a <hi>Loe</hi> of his being preſent with them <hi>alwaies,</hi> or every day, <hi>Math:</hi> 28.20; which word and phraſe, in our judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment imports a promiſe of a clear, and daily mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of what a CHRIST <hi>preſent</hi> can diſcover, and hand forth unto them: We have therefore reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through GODS <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> (being confidently &amp; comfortably perſwaded of the promiſed preſence of our MASTER with us) to <hi>put forth</hi> that <hi>power,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151511:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>the LORD hath (in this inſtance) intruſted us; That in this part of CHRISTS Church, 1 A <hi>Goſpell-Ministry</hi> may be <hi>regularly continued.</hi> 2 In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truders <hi>prevented.</hi> 3 CHRISTS Flocke <hi>preſerved,</hi> as well from diſperſion, as infection.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>
                     <hi>2</hi> By experience of divers ſad conſequents of non-ordination.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">§. 10.</note>COntraries are beſt illuſtrated by their Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. We ſhall therefore particularize ſome of the ſad co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequents, which by experience we have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to ariſe from entrance into the Miniſtry by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waies than GODS way of Ordinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 1 The moſt of thoſe, who take upon them the Miniſtry, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ordination, are far from having ſuch <hi>gifts,</hi> as are neceſſarily required in thoſe that are <hi>instructours</hi> to others. 2 Thoſe <hi>Congregations,</hi> who give this liberty to perſons unordained, are <hi>incompetent Judges</hi> of their gifts. 3 <hi>Converſion-worke</hi> went on more live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when <hi>Miniſteriall-worke</hi> was wholly in the hands of ordained men, and Church-Guides. 4 Such con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident Intruders are ſeldome without their conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>errours,</hi> not only in diſcipline, but doctrine. 5 <hi>Popery,</hi> &amp; <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> have little prevailed, but where and when, either ſuch as pretended to be Miniſters, laboured not in the word and doctrin; or ſuch as pretended to labour in the word and doctrine, were not Miniſters. 6 <hi>Enthuſiaſmes</hi> in ſuch we ſee often pretended to, and no wonder, when <hi>Learning,</hi> which in an ordinary way, ſhould furniſh with abilities, is wanting. 7 Though this <hi>Gangrene</hi> begins at the <hi>foote;</hi> yet it ſuddenly cates to the <hi>heart:</hi> we ſeldome ſee
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151511:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>any who are againſt Ordinances, Sabbaths of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, CHRIST, but ſuch as were firſt againſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained Miniſters. Some of them who without ordination pretended to be prime Preachers <hi>of</hi> CHRIST, doe now themſelves protend to <hi>be</hi> CHRIST. 8 In ſuch unordained men is eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable, not only the bublings up, but the flowings over of a <hi>Spirit of pride, &amp; ſelfe-confidence.</hi> 9 They who <hi>exclaime</hi> againſt Miniſters, as preaching for Tithes, have given ſhrewd cauſe of ſuſpition, that themſelves preached for <hi>places</hi> and <hi>employments,</hi> 10 Such unordained perſons co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly divide and breake inſunder ſuch Congregations, in which they have liberty to exerciſe. 11 They ordinarily <hi>obtrude</hi> themſelves on ſuch Congregations, as are conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly ſcrupled, and profeſſedly unſatisfied with them. 12 Many or them <hi>neglect</hi> the duties of their particular and generall <hi>Calling;</hi> and whilſt they pretend to teach whole Congregations, they omit to inſtruct their Children and Servants. 13 Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of ſuch wild and: irregular practiſes, the Ordinances of the Goſpell come to be <hi>contemned,</hi> and the offering of the LORD to be <hi>abhorred.</hi> 14 <hi>Men</hi> of <hi>learning</hi> and ability, whoſe labours might have been of ſingular and ſignall advantage, have by this meanes been <hi>ſlighted,</hi> excluded. 15 Even by <hi>naturall conſcience</hi> the prophane are convinced that duties of Religion ought to be performed, and diſtinct Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons attend them when therefore they ſee ſuch as pretend to the <hi>power</hi> of Religion, to deſpiſe the <hi>forme</hi> (which is the utmoſt their Capacities can reach) they are eaſily induced by the <hi>old Serpent</hi> to over value
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151511:9"/>the forme, and deſpiſe the power; and when they ſee other prophane ones, prize what they prize, and thoſe that pretend to the power, deſpiſe the ſame (by making it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, and of ordinary addreſs) they are rootedly hardned in their prophaneſs 16 The <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>Papists</hi> are alienated from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>Ignorance</hi> is the mother of Popiſh devotion; they therefore reſpect more the <hi>perſons</hi> of teachers than the things taughts and where theſe are contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, they are apt to repute Religion denied:</p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Unity</hi> are eſſentiall properties (in the <hi>Papiſts</hi> opinion) of the true Church; but diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Schiſme are the naturall conſequents of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordained Intruders; and where theſe are, the <hi>Papists</hi> doe readily conclude that Religion is not.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Many <hi>Papiſts,</hi> though ſo ignorant in the choiſe principles of Chriſtianity, that their faith is <hi>impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate;</hi> yet in many things (eſpecially <hi>Popiſh</hi> controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied) they clearly diſcover a greater <hi>ignorance</hi> and <hi>weakneſs</hi> in theſe Intruders; the diſcovery whereof, together with the admiration of their own dark <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſters,</hi> confirmes them in their perſwaſions againſt the Proteſtant Religion; whereof they judge rather by the weakneſs and pretences of ſuch Intruders, than by the true grounds of Proteſtant Religion.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Theſe various unordained Intruders are often <hi>contradictory,</hi> not only to each other, but to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; the obſervance whereof confirmes the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> that as there is out <hi>one</hi> truth, ſo theſe contrary waies can not be that truth.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 <hi>Scripture</hi> being wreſted by theſe <hi>unſtable</hi> intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151511:9"/>to patronize their own <hi>conceptions,</hi> the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are confirmed, that <hi>Scripture</hi> is a Judge inſufficient, and unlawfull for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon <hi>uſe,</hi> as being liable to <hi>abuſe,</hi> and if <hi>Scripture-adjudication</hi> be once rejected, carnall reaſon will invite to ſet the higheſt value on <hi>Popiſh</hi> politie.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 Theſe unordained Intruders doe uſually <hi>revile</hi> Goſpell-Miniſters, and the owners of the Goſpell-Miniſtry as Anti-Chriſtian: Now when that guilt is charged by theſe on the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> which the <hi>Proteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants</hi> charge on the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are thereby confirmed, as if they were as <hi>innocent</hi> as their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Oppoſites and Reprovers.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 Vice may be nouriſhed with the milke of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. The Goſpell-Miniſters are conſtrained by the diſtracting diſturbances of theſe Intruders to lay out ſo much of their time and ſweate in the prevention of the evil conſequences before inſtanced, that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> (who are oppoſite in the other extreame) gaine ground by this diverſion, and are eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to thinke the <hi>better</hi> of themſelves, even on this occaſion.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 Many doctrines delivered by theſe Intruders are expreſſely <hi>Popiſh;</hi> which ſome of them deliver becauſe of their <hi>ignorance</hi> and inability to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh betwixt what is <hi>Popiſh,</hi> and what not; others out of deſigne to introduce <hi>Popery</hi> without noiſe or diſcovery.</p>
                  <p>Many of theſe conſequences (we beleeve) ariſe from the nature of unſcripturall intruſion into the worke of the Miniſtry without ordination; though poſſibly others of them ariſe from the frequent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temper
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151511:10"/>and irregularity of them, who dare be ſuch Intruders; by inſtance whereof we intend not to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the diſtorted illations made by Papiſts, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſons; but to diſcover the advantage, which by this occaſion is miniſtred to the ſlye and ſubtle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuations of the crooked <hi>Serpent,</hi> and the Church-ſhattering, Soule-indangering improvement he makes of that advantage; which jointly with the ſence of our ſpeciall duty, inforceth us to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge thereof, in ordaining Miniſters.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>More, than others.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">§. 11.</note>THat <hi>we</hi> herein <hi>begin,</hi> will be no temptation (we hope) of prejudice to any Brethren; for 1. Some muſt begin. 2. <hi>England</hi> affords many <hi>prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents.</hi> 3 of all, in this County, we apprehend the opportunity to aſſociate is moſt, becauſe the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are <hi>moſt</hi> and <hi>neareſt:</hi> the neceſſity moſt, becauſe the Congregations are <hi>most</hi> and <hi>greatest;</hi> and many members of them rationally judge, <hi>that thoſe intend to climbe over the Wall, who refuſe to enter in by the Doore.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>More, than formerly.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">§. 12.</note>THat we rather ingage in this duty <hi>at preſent,</hi> than <hi>formerly,</hi> hath theſe inducements. 1. The Proteſtant Inhabitants were neceſſitated formerly to live in, or nigh Garriſons; and ſo might be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied by ſuch ordained Miniſters, as GOD had there ſet: but at preſent, they diſperſe themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves into the Country; wherefore to attend them, the increaſe of the number of Miniſters, becomes
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151511:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>neceſſary; and to that end (by GODS inſtitution) ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is neceſſary.<note place="margin">More Goſpell-Miniſters ſett<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Ireland, ſince the <hi>LORD HENRY-CROMVVELL</hi> arriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed here, and owned the public Ordinances of Christ, than in <hi>15</hi> years precedent. Thinke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him O God for good, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to all be hath done for thy People.</note> 2 Through the LORDS goodneſs, &amp; the benigne aſpect of our Magiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, Goſpell-Miniſters are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, and we finde, that both the <hi>harveſt</hi> is great, and the <hi>Labourers</hi> not ſo few as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly; who (in GODS way) muſt either ſeeke ordination from our Brethren, the <hi>Scots</hi> in <hi>Vlſter;</hi> the inconveniences whereof (the preſent State of affaires conſidered) are too obvious to need our inſtances: or from our Brethren in <hi>England;</hi> But 1 They may probably want <hi>meanes</hi> of ſupport for ſuch a journy. 2 <hi>Certificates</hi> from perſons at this diſtance, may poſſibly be counterfeited, or if true; diſcredited, becauſe the Subſcribers unknown: by the <hi>former,</hi> unfit perſons may be ordained; by the <hi>latter,</hi> fit perſons diſcouraged, if not rejected: by both, the Church of CHRIST prejudiced, and the worke of the Goſpell obſtructed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>More, than to other acts of diſcipline.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">§. 15.</note>NEither doe we thinke the procedure propoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, to ingage in the duty of <hi>Ordination,</hi> before other acts of Eccleſiaſticall <hi>diſcipline;</hi> for 1 Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we walke in the ſame method, as the <hi>reverend Aſſembly</hi> late at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> in their <hi>advice</hi> propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. 2. <hi>Ordination</hi> of Miniſters, properly and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly belongs to Miniſters. 3 Severall particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars (urged by many, under this Head of diſcipline)
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151511:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>are to us very darke: but ordination of Miniſters by Miniſters, is to all of us a clear duty: thoſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are fitteſt for further debate; this for preſent obſervance. 4 Many acts of diſcipline are only ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the <hi>well-being</hi> of the Church viſible: but ordination of Miniſters to its very being. (At leaſt conſidered as orgainz'd, or as continuing.) 5 We have mutually ingaged our ſelves to the LORD, and to each other, to improve the advantage of our fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent meetings, in wreſtling with the LORD by prayer; and conſidering and admoniſhing each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; both in relation to our particular walking, and in relation to the Flock of CHRIST, over which the HOLY GHOST hath made us Overſeers.</p>
               <p>VVE conclude with a few words of advice to the <hi>Readers</hi> of this Account of our Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and intended Practiſe; and eſpecially to our <hi>People,</hi> and the ſeverall Congregations comitted to our charge; whoſe ſpirituall improvement, flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing growth, &amp; eternall welfare in the Heavens, our very Soules doe pantingly breath after.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Let that which was the <hi>Bereans</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation, (<hi>Act:</hi> 17.11.) be yours, <hi>Search the Scriptures daily.</hi> Many places and paſſages in ſacred Writ you will ſinde quoted by us, which we intreat you to turne to, &amp; examine: A paſſing over them in haſt, &amp; with a tranſient glance, may not gaine a ſteady conſent, but leave you heſitant &amp; dubious; at leaſt in ſome of the inſtanted particulars. It's a narrow ſearch, and curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous inquiſition that tends <hi>to;</hi> &amp; terminates <hi>in</hi> a clear conviction &amp; full ſatisfaction. It's of grand concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that you be well grounded in this main Head
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151511:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Divinity. The Goſpell-Miniſtry (which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Divells ſmarting <hi>eye-ſore,</hi> being the great Engine deſigned by CHRIST to Batter down the Wails of the Kingdome of darkneſs) is on all hands beleaguer'd, aſſaulted, ſtruck at; though from ſome quarters, &amp; regions, the ſtorme be more violent and impetuous than from others. An huge duſt is raiſed by Objectors, &amp; men by great heapes looſe themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves in a miſt of dangerous miſtakes; &amp; all for want of pondering &amp; weighing things in the Ballance of the Sanctuary: However, this we may depend <hi>on,</hi> &amp; comfort our ſelves <hi>with,</hi> That <hi>it</hi> ſhall contmue till the ſecond co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of our LORD, maugre all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined &amp; boiſterous <hi>oppoſition</hi> in order to its ſubverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; abolition. When <hi>Ordinances</hi> ſhall ceaſe, then <hi>Miniſters</hi> ſhall be no more, &amp; not till then. Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Miniſters (like boughs) may be, &amp; have been lopt off by the hand of viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; but Miniſtry (like a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Tree (whoſe fruit the LORD hath appointed for the healing of the Nations) is too deeply &amp; firmely rooted, to be blowne cowne. In vaine is that Port aſſaulted, that hath a promiſe of CHRISTS pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and powerfull aſſiſtance, <hi>Math:</hi> 28.20. This is an Age abounding with <hi>ſuggeſtions</hi> &amp; <hi>inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of ſeverall ſhapes; which, if obtruded under the notion of a clearer light, &amp; an higher way of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, have a potent and captivating influence on perſons, whoſe Hearts are better than their Heads, and who have warme Affections, and but feeble In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectualls. It will be your wiſdome (abhorring all eaſy; yeelding, corrupt <hi>compliances</hi> upon the wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, unworthy account of promoting or ſecuring an
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151511:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>intereſt</hi> in the World) to have recourſe <hi>to the Law &amp; to the Teſtimony,</hi> confidently concluding, that <hi>if they speake not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them,</hi> what ever ſparkling &amp; beamy bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs may be pretended to, <hi>Eſa:</hi> 8.20.</p>
               <p n="2">2 And ſince it is a duty incumbent on the <hi>people</hi> to <hi>pray</hi> for their <hi>Paſtors,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 3.1: And ſince there is <hi>a great doore and effectuall opened,</hi> but not with out the waſpiſh activity, and retarding obſtructions of maligning <hi>adverſarias,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 16.9: And ſince we are but <hi>men, ſubject to the ſame paſſions and infirmities with your ſelves; and knowing only in part,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 13.9; &amp; our <hi>Strength</hi> no way proportionable to the <hi>weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs</hi> of that <hi>worke</hi> that lies upon us, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 2.16: we ſhall earneſtly intreate, that in your addreſſes to the Throne of Grace, you would frequently &amp; affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ionately make mention of us, &amp; importuaately pray unto the <hi>Father of Lights,</hi> that he would inlighten us with his <hi>truth,</hi> and ſhew us the way that he would have us to walke in, and teach us how we ought to behave our ſelves at ſuch a time as this is; That he would incourage our <hi>hearts,</hi> &amp; ſtrengthen our <hi>hands</hi> in his owne <hi>way</hi> and <hi>worke;</hi> That he would bleſs the <hi>ſincere,</hi> though <hi>feeble</hi> indeavours of his Servants for the propagating of the Goſpell, and promoting of the intereſt of his SON; &amp; that out of tender regard unto his Churches wellfare, he would blow upon and blaſt all anti-miniſteriall deſignes. The <hi>Harveſt</hi> is <hi>great,</hi> the <hi>Labourers few: O pray unto the LORD of the Harveſt, that he would ſend forth painfull Labourers into his Harvest,</hi> Math: 9.37; 38; and make them ſuceeſsfull for the bringing of many ſheaves into
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151511:12"/>CHRISTS barne. Our <hi>motions</hi> are <hi>ſlow,</hi> becauſe not <hi>furthered</hi> and aſſiſted by your <hi>prayers,</hi> which ſhould ſerve as <hi>oile</hi> unto our Chariot wheeles, to make them <hi>run</hi> the more <hi>ſmoothly</hi> and ſwiftly. The <hi>time</hi> that many <hi>ſpend</hi> in <hi>whiſpering, complaining, back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting, quarrelling, contending, exclaiming, cenſuring,</hi> doe you <hi>ſpend</hi> in <hi>praying. The LORD forbid that we ſhould ſin,</hi> in <hi>ceaſing</hi> to <hi>pray</hi> for <hi>you,</hi> whom we expect to be our <hi>glory,</hi> and <hi>crown</hi> of <hi>rejoicing</hi> in the preſence of our LORD JESVS CHRIST at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming: <hi>And the</hi> LORD <hi>forbid</hi> that <hi>you ſhould ſin,</hi> in <hi>ceaſing</hi> to <hi>pray</hi> for <hi>us,</hi> who <hi>watch for your Soules,</hi> as thoſe that muſt give <hi>an account;</hi> and are willing to <hi>ſpend, and to be ſpent</hi> for the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es good.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:151511:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151511:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
